207
JURNAL KAJIAN PEMBELAJARAN DAN KEILMUAN
Volume 8 Nomor 2 Tahun 2024 Halaman 207-214
p-ISSN: 2579-4299, e-ISSN: 2621-0533, DOI 10.26418/jurnalkpk.v8i2.82814
https://jurnal.untan.ac.id/index.php/jurnalkpk
EFEKTIVITAS MEDIA GAMBAR BERSERI PADA KETERAMPILAN
MENULIS NARASI
Dhelia Anggita Ningrum1, Much Arsyad Fardani2
, Nur Fajrie3
Pendidikan Guru Sekolah dasar, Universirs Muria Kudus123
Article Info ABSTRACT
Article history:
Received: 23 Juli 2024
Revised: 30 Juli 2024
Accepted: 04 September 2024
Keywords:
Narration, Serialized Image
Media, Writing Skills
This research is motivated by shortcomings of habituation using
Javanese language at school, and it is known that Javanese writing
skills possessed by students are low. The aim of this research is to
analyze the impact from application of serial picture media on writing
Javanese narrative in third grade students. This research is a mixed
research using quantitative techniques. The subject of this research is
all third grade students from SD Pati Wetan 01 lasted from 3 meetings.
Data collection techniques include observation, giving questions,
interviews, and documentation. Sample of this research totaling 31
students. The results show that there is a positive effective in use
serialized picture media on students' Javanese narrative writing skills.
This can be seen from the Paired Sample t Test which shows a
significance value of 0.000. Because the significance value is less than
0.05. it is concluded that way study produces a significant effect in the
application of serial image media on the skills of writing Javanese
narrative learners.
Copyright © 2024 Dhelia Anggita Ningrum, Much Arsyad Fardani,Nur Fajrie
🖂 Corresponding Author:
Dhelia Anggita Ningrum, Much Arsyad Fardani, Nur Fajrie
Universitas Muria Kudus, Jl. Lkr. Utara, Kayuapuh Kulon, Gondangmanis, Kec. Bae, Kab. Kudus, Jawa
Tengah, Kudus
Email: 202033312@std.umk.ac.id1
, arsyad.fardani@umk.ac.id2
, nur.fajrie@umk.ac.id3
PENDAHULUAN
Pendidikan ialah suatu keharusan untuk seseorang sebab pada dasarnya seseorang lahir
keadaan awalnya tidak memiliki kekuatan dan tak dapat bangun tanpa pertolongan orang lain
(Natanti, Pratiwi, & Fardani, 2023). Pendidikan memiliki kemampuan untuk meningkatkan
kualitas hidup manusia dengan menciptakan individu yang memiliki potensi dan kreatif (Muttaqin
& Faishol, 2018). Selain itu, proses pendidikan yang baik akan menghasilkan gagasan inovatif
untuk meningkatkan kualitas hidup. Sangat penting untuk mengembangkan pendidikan. Proses
kegiatan belajar mengajar dalam pendidikan sangat penting. Untuk mengetahui seseorang sudah
mengerti atau belum maka cara yang dilakukan yaitu belajar. Belajar mampu menambah
ketrampilan dan kecakapan seseorang (Wijayanto, Utaminingsih, & Fardani, 2023). Tujuan
pembelajaran sebagai cara supaya kualitas sesorang dapat meningkat (Ulfah, 2022). Dalam proses
belajar tenaga pendidik dan peserta didik wajib bekerja sama agar tujuan pembelajaran terwujud
(Tyas, Fardani, & Kironoratri, 2024).